Myrthe Reuver

Computational Linguist, Data Scientist, PhD Candidate

I am a PhD (started: Sept 2020) at the Free University of Amsterdam (VU), advisors: prof. dr. Antske Fokkens (VU) and dr. Suzan Verberne (Leiden University). My research is on NLP to support democracy in news recommendation. My interest is in societally and scientifically responsible NLP in complex domains.

♦ https://myrthereuver.github.io/ 🖂

☑ myrthe.reuver[at]vu.nl

• myrthereuver

Twitter: @myrthereuver

Research Experience

PhD candidate: Diverse News Recommendation

Amsterdam

Free University of Amsterdam (VU)

Sept 2020 - present

o PhD project on diversity in news recommender systems. Intention to work with language models to automatically detect diversity in news texts. Supervised by prof. dr. Antske Fokkens of the CLTL research group at the Free University of Amsterdam and dr. Suzan Verberne at Leiden University

Graduation Projects Clinical Natural Language Processing

Deventer

 $Topicus\ Health care$

Dec 2019 - Sept 2020

- o MSc thesis on classification of complaint category in emergency GP triage (huisartsenpost)
- o ResMA thesis on detection of smoking status from EMRs with weak supervision & transfer learning

ResMA Research Internship: Classifying Urban Legends

Amsterdam

Meertens Institute

Feb 2019 - July 2019

 Results: a popular science article in Neerlandistiek, a simple interface demo for the model, a conference presentation at the DHBenelux conference in Liège (September 2019), and a poster presentation at CLIN30 (Computational Linguistics in the Netherlands) in January 2020.

Education

Master of Science (MSc) Cognitive Science & Artificial Intelligence

Tilburg

Tilburg University

2018 - 2020

- GPA: 7.9 / 10 (with distinction)
- o Thesis: "What Kind of Emergency? Complaint Labels for Dutch Short Clinical Texts" (Grade: 8/10)
- o Courses (selection): Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Advanced Data Processing with Python

Research MA Linguistics, track: Language & Speech Technology

Nijmegen

Radboud University

2017 - 2020

- GPA: 8.3 / 10 (cum laude)
- o Thesis: "Finding the Smoke Signal: Smoking Status Extraction & Classification" (Grade: 8 / 10)
- o Internship: Classifying Urban Legends at the Meertens Institute (Grade: 9 / 10)
- o Certificate: Interdisciplinary Honours Program for Master's Students "Thinking Machines in Healthcare"
- o Courses (selection): Text & Multimedia Mining, Language & Speech Technology, Advanced Statistics in R

BA English Language & Culture, specialization: Linguistics

Nijmegen

 $Radboud\ University$

2014 - 2017

- o GPA: 8.6 / 10 (cum laude)
- o certificate BA Honours Program: 2-year Text Mining Project + Summerschool Aarhus University, Denmark.

Bachelor of Journalism, first-year diploma

 \mathbf{Ede}

Christelijke Hogeschool Ede (CHE)

2012 - 2013

Radio Presenter at "Radio Almelo" (AAFM)

HAVO (higher general secondary education), Culture & Society profile

Almelo

OPDC 't Nijrees Almelo

2007 - 2012

Teaching

Teacher "Programming in Python for Text"

Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam

prof. dr. Antske Fokkens

Sept 2021 - Nov 2021

 A first programming course in Python for both BA and MA students in Text Mining, with a focus on basic analysis with (data with) text. Tasks included: updating material from previous years, lecturing on more advanced topics: errors, nested data structures, and XML.

Teaching Assistant BA course "Information Science"

Radboud University, Nijmegen

prof. dr. Martha Larson

April 2018 - June 2020

 A first-year bachelor's course about the basics of (digital) information science, data, privacy, algorithms and machine translation. Tasks: leading practical sessions, lecturing segments of lectures + designing, preparing and grading exercises, assignments, and exams.

Events

Winning team Hackathon "Diverse Recommendation"

Virtual

NPO and Media Perspectives

October 2020

- A 24-hour hackathon on designing a topic, viewpoint, and content diverse news & media recommender for Dutch public broadcaster NPO. 5 teams of Data Scientists and researchers competing.
- Won the hackathon with an interdisciplinary team of philosophers, communication scientists, and computationals (Marijn Sax, Felicia Loecherbacher, Sanne Vrijenhoek and Nicolas Mattis)

Information Technology (ICT) with Industry research week

Leiden

Lorentz Centre and NWO

January 2019

- o Full week of research teams working with an industry partner on their technology-related research challenge. Participated in developing a prototype of an automatic keyword classifier for the National Library (Koninklijke Bibliotheek, KB).
- o Results: a demo prototype, a report, and an NWO Science vlog about my experiences.

Leadership and Academic Service

On-site student volunteer

Amsterdam & online (hybrid)

RecSys2021

27 Sept 2021 - 1 Oct 2021

o Tasks: guiding attendees, monitoring the live stream, welcoming + registration of attendees

Founder & Editor-in-Chief

Nijmegen

RU:ts Student Linguistics Journal

Sept 2018 - Sept 2020

 Together with fellow master's students Iris Faber / Sander Nederveen, started a journal where students are authors, editors, and peer reviewers.

Skills

- Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing
- (Academic) Writing
- Public Speaking and Presenting

Languages

- Python including sklearn & pandas, & R proficient
- o html & css, familiar
- o Dutch, mothertongue, (Academic) English, C2 (near-Native)
- o German, B2 (decent), Latin, B1 (basic)

Communicating Research Outcomes

Conference Talks (Peer Reviewed Abstracts)

- o Myrthe Reuver, Suzan Verberne, Roser Morante and Antske Fokkens. 9 July 2021. "Viewpoints in the news: claim detection for diverse news recommendation." **Poster** at Computational Linguistics in the Netherlandsa (CLIN) 31 (Online), 9 July 2021.
- Myrthe Reuver, Iris Hendrickx, Jeroen Kuijpers. "Smoking Status Detection with a Pre-Trained Transformer and Weak Supervision in Dutch Electronic Patient Files." Computational Linguistics in the Netherlandsa (CLIN) 31 (Online), 9 July 2021.
- o Reuver, Myrthe. "How Similar are Poodles in the Microwave? Classification of Urban Legend Types".

 Poster at Computational Linguistics in the Netherlands (CLIN) 30, Utrecht, January 2020.
- o Reuver, Myrthe. "Making the Computer Understand Urban Legend Types (And Making Humans Understand the Computer)". Moving Humanities Graduate Conference, Nijmegen: 24 October 2019.
- Reuver, Myrthe. "Amputation or Accident? Classifying Dutch Urban Legends into Story Types with a Hierarchical Classifier". Digital Humanities BeNeLuX, Liège: 13 Sept 2019.
- o Reuver, Myrthe. "Whose Gender is It? Possessive Pronoun Errors by Portuguese L2 speakers of English." 13th TWIST Student Conference in Linguistics, Leiden. 13 April 2019.
- o Reuver, Myrthe. "First-Person Visibility: Ælfric's Pronouns in his Prefaces.", StuTs Student Linguistics Conference, Nijmegen. 24 November 2017.

Invited Talks

 Reuver, Myrthe. "Hackathons, Shared Tasks, and Papers: Collaboration and Interdisciplinarity with Data on Complex Problems". Free University of Amsterdam, University Library Data Conversations/ Online. 7 April 2021

Popular Science

- Myrthe Reuver, Nicolas Mattis. (2020) "Hackers of Science: Lessons from interdisciplinary science in a Hackathon" Socializing Science, blog.
- o Myrthe Reuver. (2019) "Hoe een computer broodjeaapverhalen leert categoriseren." Vertelcultuur Online.
- o Myrthe Reuver. Vlog research week "ICT with Industry". https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-m92LxE5hQ4

Reports (Not Peer Reviewed)

- o Myrthe Reuver, Nicolas Mattis. (2021). "Implementing Evaluation Metrics Based on Theories of Democracy in News Comment Recommendation (Hackathon Report)" In: Proceedings of the EACL Hackashop on News Media Content Analysis and Automated Report Generation (co-located at EACL 2021, online). Association of Computational Linguistics, p. 134–139.
- o Anthony Burton, Elena Aversa, Alessandra Facchin, Ivana Emily Škoro, Henri Mütschele, **Myrthe Reuver**, Shenglang Qing. (2019). "Streams of the Deep Web: Rebel Media, YouTube, and the algorithmic shaping of media ecosystems." Digital Methods Wiki, UvA Summerschool.
- o Brandsen, A., Kleppe, M., Veldhoen, S., Zijdeman, R., Huurman, H., Vos, H. De, Goes, K., Huang, L., Kim, A., Mesbah, S., **Reuver, M.**, Wang, S., Hendrickx, I. (2019). "Brinkeys.." KB Lab:The Hague, the Netherlands.

Publications

Myrthe Reuver, Antske Fokkens, and Suzan Verberne. No nlp task should be an island: Multi-disciplinarity for diversity in news recommender systems. In *Proceedings of the EACL Hackashop on News Media Content Analysis and Automated Report Generation*, pages 45–55, 2021.

Myrthe Reuver, Nicolas Mattis, Marijn Sax, Suzan Verberne, Nava Tintarev, Natali Helberger, Judith Moeller, Sanne Vrijenhoek, Antske Fokkens, and Wouter van Atteveldt. Are we human, or are we users? the role of natural language processing in human-centric news recommenders that nudge users to diverse content. In *Proceedings of the 1st Workshop on NLP for Positive Impact, co-located at ACL-IJCNLP 2021*, pages 47–59, 2021.

Myrthe Reuver, Suzan Verberne, Morante Roser, and Antske Fokkens. forthcoming at Argument Mining

 $\begin{tabular}{ll} workshop @ EMNLP 2021 Is stance detection topic-independent and cross-topic generalizable?- a reproduction study. In 8th Workshop on Argument Mining, co-located with EMNLP 2021, 2021. \\ \end{tabular}$